Guide to the Norman Holmes Pearson Collection of "Art for the Wrong Reason"
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Norman Holmes Pearson Collection of "Art for the Wrong Reason"
1833-1979
YCAL MSS 1031
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
63
(6 boxes) + 14 Art
Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975
Boschère, Jean de, 1878-1953
Chesterton, G. K. (Gilbert Keith), 1874-1936
Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910
Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1894-1962
Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970
Du Maurier, George, 1834-1896
Grass, Günter, 1927-2015
H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1886-1961
Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962
Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885
Jarry, Alfred, 1873-1907
Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930
Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997
Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957
Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931
Masefield, John, 1878-1967
Miller, Henry, 1891-1980
Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972
Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980
Russell, George William Erskine, 1853-1919
Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950
Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863
Valtman, Edmund S., 1914-
Welch, Denton
Wiens, Paul, 1922-1982
Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963
Wolfe, Tom, 1930-2018
Related Materials
Norman Holmes Pearson Papers (YCAL MSS 899), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Norman Holmes Pearson (1909-1975)
Norman Holmes Pearson (Yale 1932, 1941 PhD), professor of English and American Studies at Yale University and officer in the United States Office of Strategic Services during World War II. Pearson collaborated with Yale University Library curator Donald Gallup to develop the Yale Collection of American Literature, playing an instrumental role in the library's acquisition of the papers of H. D. and Bryher.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by author.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains sixty-three sketches, drawings, paintings, and prints acquired by Yale faculty member Norman Holmes Pearson not for their aesthetic or artistic merit, but because they were created by poets and other authors; he titled his collection "Art for the Wrong Reason." The works were executed in crayon, gouache, graphite, ink, charcoal, oil, and watercolor on paper, board, canvas, and panel, by fifty-three writers including E. E. Cummings, George Du Maurier, Victor Hugo, D. H. Lawrence, and Katherine Anne Porter, with multiple works by John Dos Passos, H. D., Herman Hesse, Denise Levertov, Wyndham Lewis, John Masefield, Henry Miller, and William Makepeace Thackeray. Among the drawings are portraits, self-portraits, or caricatures of G. K. Chesterton, Hugh Hefner, Henry Miller, J. M. Mitchison, Norman Holmes Pearson, Bernard Shaw, and Osbert Sitwell.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Chiefly bequest of Norman Holmes Pearson (Yale 1932, 1941 PhD), 1975. Other additions noted at folder level.
Artists -- Portraits; Authors -- Portraits; Montagnola (Switzerland) -- Pictorial works; Passaic River (N.J.) -- Pictorial works; Caricatures; Drawings (visual works); Etchings (prints); Lithographs; Oil paintings (visual works); Portraits; Self-portraits; Watercolors (paintings); Artists; Authors; Boschère, Jean de, 1878-1953; Chesterton, G. K. (Gilbert Keith), 1874-1936; Chesterton, G. K. (Gilbert Keith), 1874-1936 -- Portraits; Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910; Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1894-1962; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970; Du Maurier, George, 1834-1896; Grass, Günter, 1927-2015; H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1886-1961; Hefner, Hugh M. (Hugh Marston), 1926- -- Caricatures and cartoons; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885; Jarry, Alfred, 1873-1907; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931; Masefield, John, 1878-1967; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980 -- Portraits; Mitchison, J. M. -- Portraits; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980; Russell, George William Erskine, 1853-1919; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950 -- Portraits; Sitwell, Osbert, 1892-1969 -- Portraits; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Valtman, Edmund S., 1914-; Welch, Denton; Wiens, Paul, 1922-1982; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Wolfe, Tom, 1930-2018; Wylie, Elinor, 1885-1928 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975
- Anderson, Sherwood, [Cross-section of a log], watercolor on paper (1980.131.42), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 34)
- Ballantyne, R. M., "After the Deer," watercolor on paper (1980.131.26), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  With inscriptions on verso to describe the costumes depicted.
- Belloc, Hilaire, "Pictorem Male Nata Turba Ridet...," ink and watercolor on board and paper (1980.131.31), 1897 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 35)
- Benet, William Rose, [Whale gallant], watercolor on board (1980.131.54), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 36)
- Boschère, Jean de, [Illustration for The Arabian Nights ], watercolor on paper (1980.131.14), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 2)
- Bukowski, Charles, [Man seated in room], ink on paper (1980.131.57), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 3)
- Chesterton, G. K., [Self-portrait], graphite and crayon on board (1980.131.53), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 4)
  Inscribed at lower right: "GCK to AB." Inscribed on verso: "From Doran Collection."
- Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, [One-eyed dog], ink on paper (1980.131.18), 1895 (Box 7 (Art))
  Inscribed: "Executed instantaneously and blindfolded by / Truly Yours / Mark Twain / (Educated artist)."
- Coates, Robert, "Portrait of the Artist Reading His Favorite Author," graphite on paper (1980.131.56), 1928 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 5)
  Inscribed "To Althea Thurber"
- Cocteau, Jean, [Sketch on "Santo-Sospir" letterhead], ink on paper (1980.131.40), 1960 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 6)
- Corso, Gregory, [Forest scene], crayon on paper (1980.131.52), undated (Box 8 (Art))
- Cummings, E. E., [Silver Lake, New Hampshire], watercolor on paper (1980.131.1), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 37)
- Dos Passos, John
  - [Manhattan skyscrapers], gouache on paper (1980.131.30), undated (Box 9 (Art))
  - "Recollection of the Aurescu -- Pays-Basque, 1923," gouache on paper (1980.131.9), 1965 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 38)
    Inscribed on verso: "Recollection of the Aurescu / -- Pays Basque 1923 / for Norman Pearson / Nov 1965." Dos Passos refers to the Aurresku, a traditional Basque dance.
- Douglas, Norman, [Gardeners], graphite on paper (1980.131.46), undated (Box 10 (Art))
- Du Maurier, George, [Autograph letter to "Willi" with drawings of dogs], ink on paper (1980.131.58), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 7)
- Grass, Günter, [Group of clothed skeletons talking], lithograph (1980.131.8), undated (Box 11 (Broadside))
- H. D. (Hilda Doolittle)
  - [Wild cyclamen], graphite on paper (1980.131.17), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 8)
  - "Homage to Georges Braque," crayon on paper (1980.131.4), 1958 (Box 12 (Art))
- Hesse, Hermann
  - "Aprikosenblute I," watercolor on paper (1980.131.45), 1926 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 9)
  - "Juli, Abend," watercolor and crayon on paper (1980.131.12), 1925 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 39)
  - [Montagnola, Tessin], watercolor on paper (1980.131.35), 1931 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 10)
  - "Sonnenaufgang überm Nebel," watercolor on paper (1980.131.25), 1933 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 11)
  - "Souvenir pour Bryher," watercolor on paper (1980.131.13), 1922 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 40)
  - [View from terrace, Montagnola, Tessin], watercolor on paper (1980.131.44), 1934 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 12)
- Hodgson, Ralph, [Two profile portraits], graphite on paper (1980.131.59.1-.2), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 13)
  Both inscribed on verso
- Horgan, Paul, [From the Pont-Royal Hotel, Paris], watercolor on paper (1980.131.38), 1959 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 14)
  Inscribed at lower right: "Paul / du rue Montalembert / Paris / 17 oct / '59"
- Hugo, Victor, [At low tide], ink on paper (1980.131.51), 1842 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 15)
- Jarry, Alfred, "César-Antéchrist.," ink on paper (1980.131.19), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 16)
- Knight, Eric, [Roses], tempera on board (1980.131.3), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 17)
- Lawrence, D. H., "Arabella!," watercolor on paper (1980.131.28), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 41)
- Levertov, Denise
  - [Sketch of trees], ink on paper (1980.131.20), 1973 (Box 13 (Art))
  - "A Tree Recalls Orpheus," ink on paper (not numbered), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 42)
- Lewis, Wyndham
  - [Abstraction], ink on paper (1980.131.43), 1924 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 18)
  - [Portrait of John Murdoch Mitchison], charcoal on paper (1980.131.34), circa 1931 (Box 14 (Art))
    Inscribed below: "Portrait of my son Murdoch, by Wyndham Lewis / in late 1931 or 1932 / Naomi Mitchinson"
  - [Portrait of Osbert Sitwell], watercolor and graphite on paper (1980.131.11), 1920 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
- Lindsay, Vachel, "The Dream of King David in Heaven...," watercolor and ink on paper (1980.131.33), undated (Box 15 (Art))
- Masefield, John
  - [Clipper ship], watercolor, tempera, and graphite on paper (1980.131.49), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 43)
  - [Clipper ship], watercolor, tempera, and graphite on paper (1980.131.50), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 44)
- Martinelli, Sheri, "Leucothoe," ink on panel (1980.131.24), 1958 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 49)
  Inscribed on verso: "For H.D. in Keeping until I get the 'Magic Head' to her Sheri end June 1958"
- Miller, Henry
  - [Self-portrait], watercolor on paper (1980.131.5), undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 45)
  - "Tropical," watercolor on paper (1980.131.6), 1955 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 46)
- Moore, Marianne, [Flower drawings], watercolor on paper (not numbered), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 20)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Removed from Marianne Moore correspondence in the H.D. Papers (YCAL MSS 24) and placed in the Pearson Collection.
- Porter, Katherine Anne, [Caricature of Elinor Wylie], ink on paper (1980.131.7), 1927 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 21)
- Proust, Marcel, "Fuad Pasha," ink on paper (1980.131.48), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 22)
- Rannit, Aleksis, "Lesbos," ink on paper (1980.131.47), 1959 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 23)
- Reid, Mayne, [Portrait of a man], lithograph (1980.131.10), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 24)
  Inscribed in ink on mount: "To Captain Frederick Brockwell from his friend Mayne Reid."
- Ruskin, John, [Mountainous stream on coast], graphite on paper (1980.131.21), undated (Box 16 (Art))
- Russell, George William Erskine, [Children on the Irish dunes], oil on canvas (1980.131.2), undated (Box 17 (Art))
- Seton, Ernest Thompson, [Autograph with paw print], ink on paper (1980.131.60), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 25)
- Shaw, Bernard, [Self-portrait as Don Quixote], watercolor on paper (1980.131.39), undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 47)
  Inscribed on separate sheet (with drawing): "This will do with one alteration / The donkey is blind. / His eyes should be straining at the / carrots, and his ears should be / also strained towards them rigidly. / [with drawing of donkey]"
- Stevenson, Robert Louis, "Vailima," watercolor on paper (1980.131.22), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 26)
- Thackeray, William Makepeace
  - [Man and woman at well], ink on paper (1980.131.23), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 27)
  - "Road to Charmouth," ink and graphite on paper (1980.131.55), 1833 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 28)
- Valery, Paul, "Piazza Cavour," ink on paper (1980.131.37), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 29)
- Valtman, Edmund S., [Caricature of Norman Holmes Pearson], ink on paper (1980.131.27), 1974 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 30)
  Inscribed: "For Aleksis, / affectionately / Norman Holmes Pearson" and "Aleksis Raninit'ile / sõpruses / Edmund Valtman / 11. aug. 1976."
- Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, [Figure studies after R. Doyle], etching (1980.131.16), 1865 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 31)
- Warren, Rosanna, [Olive tree], graphite on paper (1980.131.15), 1976 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 32)
- Welch, Denton, [Still life], oil on canvasboard (1980.131.29), undated (Box 18 (Art))
- Wiens, Paul, "Abstract Composition," ink on paper (1980.131.61), 1979 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 33)
  Inscribed at bottom in pencil: "Paul Wiens, the German poet, gave me this drawing and I am giving this drawing to Norman Holmes Pearson Collection. Alexis Rannit, 3/4/1982." Inscribed on verso: "Paul Wiens / Abstract Composition / Felt-tip pen / color drawing of 1979 / made during the International / PEN-Congress in Rio de Janeiro."
- Wilder, Thornton, [Sketch made during W. S. Lewis reading, Farmington, CT, 5 April 1962], graphite on paper (1980.131.36) (Box 19 (Art))
- Williams, William Carlos, [Scene on the Passaic River], oil on panel (1980.131.32), undated (Box 20 (Art))
- Wolfe, Tom, [Caricature of Hugh Hefner for "King of the Status Dropouts" in The Pump House Gang ], ink on board with collage (1980.131.41), circa 1965 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 48)
  Inscribed "For Norman Holmes Pearson, this American Study of the stroke magazine publisher Hugh Hefner, offered with a deep bow and a tip of the hat, by Tom Wolfe Christmas 1974."